Guide to the Peter Palmquist Collection of Women in Photography
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter Palmquist collection of women in photography
1840-2017
WA MSS S-2600
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
337.62
(520 boxes) + 6 broadside folders
This collection consists of biographical files collected by Peter Palmquist for over thirty thousand women involved in photography and photographic materials that represent the work of nearly two thousand women. Palmquist began the Women in Photography International Archive in 1971 as a systematic study of women photographers in California, which then extended to the American West. By 1994, he broadened the collection to include women involved in photography since its beginning to contemporary times around the world. He included amateur and commercial photographers, studio assistants, retouchers, colorists, photojournalists, and filmmakers, as well as early critics of photography and characters in literary works.
Palmquist, Peter E.
Women in Photography (U.S.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Peter E. Palmquist on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1999.
Includes a gift of Penny Brogden, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Books and periodicals formerly in the personal library of Peter Palmquist are accessible via the library catalog by searching special collections for the search string: "Palmquist, Peter E., Ownership."
Peter E. Palmquist (1936-2003)
A photographer, collector, and historian of photography, Peter Eric Palmquist was born in Oakland, California on September 23, 1936. In 1944, he moved with his family to Ferndale, California, and he spent most of his life in Humboldt County. During adolescence, Palmquist trained himself in photography. He served in the United States Army as a photographer from 1955 to 1959, mainly with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe in Paris, France. Palmquist worked briefly as a photographer for the state government of California from 1959-1961. From 1961 until his retirement in 1989, Palmquist worked as a staff photographer for Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, where he also graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in Art in 1965.
From 1971 until his death, Palmquist collected textual materials and hundreds of thousands of photographic items documenting the practice and occupation of photography from its beginning through the turn of the twenty-first century. He had particular interests in early California photographers, photographers of the American West, and women photographers.
A self-trained researcher and historian of photography, Palmquist organized more than a hundred exhibitions and wrote more than three hundred articles and a hundred monographs. He was a founding editor of The Daguerreian Annual; president of the National Stereoscopic Association.
Peter Palmquist began the Women in Photography International Archive in 1971 as a systematic study of women photographers in California, which then extended to the American West. By 1994, he broadened the collection to include women involved in photography since its beginning to contemporary times around the world. He included amateur and commercial photographers, studio assistants, retouchers, colorists, photojournalists, and filmmakers, as well as early critics of photography and characters in literary works. For the collection, he and his assistants collected biographical and photographic materials that document the work and lives of these individuals.
Palmquist died January 13, 2003, in Oakland.
Women in Photography International
The collection includes the records of Women in Photography International is an educational nonprofit group founded in 1981 by Thea Litsios, Orah Moore, Mary McNally, and other wmen photographers in Los Angeles, California. The professional organization serves women photographers, photographic educators, photography students, and gallery owners around the world. It promotes women photographers and their work through programs, exhibitions, juried competitions and publications. The organization donated the bulk of its records to the Women in Photography International Archive maintained by Peter Palmquist in 1991, and supplemented by additional material over the ensuing years.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Palmquist's efforts to identify, collect, preserve, and disseminate information about women in photography.
The Biographical Files series provide excellent name-based access to information about more than thirty thousand individual women involved in photography. The biographical files allow for broad and deep studies of women in photography. Some files are not extensive. They derive from secondary material collected by Palmquist, as well as biographical profiles, professional vitae, advertising items, exhibition announcements, and reviews provided by photographers and historians of photography. The biographical materials also provides limited information for regional photographers, especially in California and the American West, and temporal studies of women photographers. A database https://libapp.library.yale.edu/Palmquist provides individual name access to women with biographical files in this series, as well as any available information regarding their aliases, working locations, life dates, and work dates.
The Photographic Materials series includes photographic images created by more than two thousand individual women photographers. These materials include vintage photographs created by women photographers, with a majority created before 1910, as well as copy photographs created by Palmquist. The majority of the early vintage photography represents the work of studio photographers and amateur photographers. The collection also includes a significant representation of works by art photographers.
The Publication and Exhibition Research series includes research files compiled by Palmquist to support projects on topics related to women photographers, including his book, With Nature's Children: Emma B. Freeman (1880-1928): Camera and Brush (1977). The final series consists of the records of Women in Photography International, a nonprofit organization founded in 1981 to serve women photographers, photographic educators, photography students and gallery owners.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Biographical Materials, 1971-2003. II. Photographic Materials, 1971-2003. III. Publication and Exhibition Research, 1974-2003. IV. Women in Photography International Records, 1980-2003.
Photographers -- Biography; Photographers -- California; Photographers -- West (U.S.); Photography -- Bio-bibliography; Photography -- California; Photography -- West (U.S.); Photography, Artistic; Women photographers -- Bio-bibliography; Women photographers -- Biography; Women photographers -- Miscellanea; Women photographers -- Pictorial works; Women photographers -- History; Women photographers -- 19th century; Women photographers -- 20th Century; Women photographers -- California; Women photographers -- West (U.S.); Women photographers; California -- Pictorial works; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Biography files; Negatives (photographs); Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Slides (photographs); Transparencies; Palmquist, Peter E.; Women in Photography (U.S.); Women in Photography International Archive
- Biographical Materials, 1971-2003; Series I; (219 boxes)
  Arrangement
  This series is organized into five subseries: Biographical Files, Biographical Volumes, Volumes About Women Photographers in General, Publicity about Exhibitions and Lectures, and Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists principally of biographical files and volumes that document over thirty thousand women involved with photography from circa 1840 to 2003. Palmquist and his assistants compiled much of the material from secondary sources between 1971 and 2003. Biographical material for many of the women photographers in the late twentieth century derived from materials collected by the Women in Photography International organization in the course of developing exhibitions.
  This series also includes bound volumes containing information about women photographers in general and a small group of correspondence between Palmquist and his assistants with scholars about women involved in photography.
  - Biographical Files, 1971-2003; (94 boxes)
    This subseries is organized alphabetically by personal or coporate name. Women with no identifiable surname are arranged alphabetically by their first name at the end of the subseries.
    The files are housed in the original letter-size folders used by Palmquist, occasionally supplemented by folders provided by the processing archivists where no folder previously existed or the original folder had deteriorated beyond repair.
    Oversize items are housed in Series II within the subseries, Oversize Photographic and Biographical Materials.
    This portion of the finding aid provides ranges of boxes holding hundreds of individual biographical files. Researchers may consult a database https://libapp.library.yale.edu/Palmquist that provides individual name access to women represented in this subseries, as well as any available information regarding their aliases, working locations, life dates, and work dates.
    The contents of individual biographical files range from solely providing the name of a woman to more comprehensive information, such as her life and work dates and her working locations, as well as professional or personal acquaintances.
    The files provide particularly strong documentation for women photographers in California and the North American West, but also include information on photographers from around the world.
    - A., L. B., to Alexander, Dorothy (Box 1)
    - Alexander, Helen A., to Anderson, Ruth Matilda (Box 2)
    - Anderson, Shirley J., to Arzner, Dorothy (Box 3)
    - Asbury, Dana, to Baker, Elsie D. (Box 4)
    - Baker, Fanny, to Barre, Ethel H. (Box 5)
    - Barrell, Sarah Webb, to Beck, T. (Box 6)
    - Becker, Mrs., to Berger, Harriet (Box 7)
    - Berger, Iola, to Bird, Sarah (Box 8)
    - Birdsall, Jeanne, to Boesen, Anna C. (Box 9)
    - Boffin, Tessa, to Bowlby, F. E., Miss (Box 10)
    - Bowler, Elizabeth, to Brigman, Anne Wardrope (Box 11)
    - Brignell, Miss, to Brown, Winfred (Box 12)
    - Brownback, Bertha, to Burke, Valerie (Box 13)
    - Burkey, Bonny H., to Calverley, Alice M. (Box 14)
    - Calvert, Alvida, to Carr, Hannah (Box 15)
    - Carr, Ione V., to Chapman, W., Mrs. (Box 16)
    - Chappard, Daniella, to Clark, Susan Mullally (Box 17)
    - Clarke, Mrs., to Coleman, Willette (Box 18)
    - Colemorgan, A., Mrs., to Cooney, Mary C. (Box 19)
    - Cooper, Miss, to Crawford, Florence Summerbell (Box 20)
    - Crawford, Garie, to Daams, Adèle (Box 21)
    - Dabill, Melanie, to Davis, Sylvia A. (Box 22)
    - Davis, Thelma, to Dennis, Sarah (Box 23)
    - Dennison, Dorothy, to Doherty, Marie E. (Box 24)
    - Dohm, Mary C., to Duncan, Beverly (Box 25)
    - Duncan, J. I., Mrs, to Edwards, Helen (Box 26)
    - Edwards, J. H., Mrs., to Ennis, Adelaide (Box 27)
    - Enos, Chris, to Farrell, Sherrie (Box 28)
    - Farrer, Edith Strait, to Fiore, Jennifer Lynne (Box 29)
    - Firestone, Brooks., to Foskett, Maggie (Box 30)
    - Fosse, Marlen, to Frisse, Jane Courtney (Box 31)
    - Frissell, Emily C., to Garrido, Rafaela (Box 32)
    - Garrin, Janice, to Gilman, Patricia (Box 33)
    - Gilmore, Susan, to Gore, Emma (Box 34)
    - Gorelik-Carson, Sonia, to Greve, Ruth (Box 35)
    - Grewell, Abbie J., to Hahn, Nellie (Box 36)
    - Hahnenkamp, Maria, to Harcey, Myrtle M. (Box 37)
    - Harcourt, Cosette, to Havens, W., Mrs. (Box 38)
    - Havránková, Milota, to Henry, Julia Biddle (Box 39)
    - Henry, Louise Maud, to Hilty, Wendy (Box 40)
    - Himmel, Lizzie, to Honegger, Ruth (Box 41)
    - Honey, Nancy, to Huckell, Lisa (Box 42)
    - Huddleson, Patricia, to Iturbide, Graciela (Box 43)
    - Iuvone, Mary, to Jewell, Holly J. (Box 44)
    - Jewett, Elizabeth Caroline, to Jonsson, Lisa (Box 45)
    - Joo, Eunsuk, to Keeler, Tracy (Box 46)
    - Keeling, Susan, to King, Beatrice Presswood (Box 47)
    - King, C. C., Mrs., to Koss, Veronica S. (Box 48)
    - Kost, Julieanne, to Lamb, Rita (Box 49)
    - Lamba, Jaqueline, to Lawrence, Irene (Box 50)
    - Lawrence, Jo Anne, to Leone, Lisa (Box 51)
    - Leopold, Susan, to Litjens, Emily (Box 52)
    - Litle, Alev, to Lubke, Sophie (Box 53)
    - Lublin, Lea, to Maeder, Suzie E. (Box 54)
    - Maes, Freya, to Marsh, Chrissy Ogden (Box 55)
    - Marsh, Cynthia, to May, Violet (Box 56)
    - Mayben, Elizabeth M., to McHenry, Ada M. (Box 57)
    - McHugh, Eva L., to Mendenhall, Ruth Dyar (Box 58)
    - Mendes, Janet, to Miller, Sylvia Rothenberger (Box 59)
    - Miller, Vicki, to Moore, Cora (Box 60)
    - Moore, Dana, to Mudge, Tressie (Box 61)
    - Mueller, Barbara, to Nelson, Minnie (Box 62)
    - Nelson, Nellie, to Norman, Rosamund (Box 63)
    - Normand, Mabel, to O'Neal, Olive (Box 64)
    - O'Neil, Carol, to Pardington, Fiona (Box 65)
    - Paretzkin, Brita, to Peck, Emma (Box 66)
    - Peck, Frank, Mrs., to Phyfer, Connie Noyes (Box 67)
    - Pia, Paule, to Posener, Jill (Box 68)
    - Posner, Iris, to Radell, Bertha L. (Box 69)
    - Rademacher, Nathalie, to Reeves, Mildred (Box 70)
    - Reeves, Nana, to Rigdon, Alice (Box 71)
    - Riggins, Marie, to Rogers, Helene (Box 72)
    - Rogers, I. L., Mrs., to Royce, Roana (Box 73)
    - Royer, Fanchon, to Sampson, M. W., Mrs. (Box 74)
    - Sams, Kelley, to Schmeken, Regina (Box 75)
    - Schmerl, Irene, to Seely, Nell O. (Box 76)
    - Seewald, Hanna, to Sherman, Susan (Box 77)
    - Sheron, Georgia, to Skelton, Marlys (Box 78)
    - Skertchly, M. C., Miss, to Smith, Rosalind (Box 79)
    - Smith, S. D., Mrs., to Sperry, Myra E. (Box 80)
    - Spesert, Mary Jane, to Stevens, Amanda E. (Box 81)
    - Stevens, Beatrice, to Stuart, W. F., Mrs. (Box 82)
    - Stubblefield, Lottie, to Tangora, Mary Alicia (Box 83)
    - Tani, Diane, to Thompson, Lou W., Mrs. (Box 84)
    - Thompson, M., Mrs., to Trembath, Hetty (Box 85)
    - Tremblay, Elene, to Utter-Grigus, Deanna (Box 86)
    - Uttermohlen, Mary Lou, to Von zur Muehlen, Bernis (Box 87)
    - Vonier, Jeanette, to Ward, Catharine Weed Barnes (Box 88)
    - Ward, Cathy, to Weil, Mathilde (Box 89)
    - Weil, Susan, to White, Dora A. (Box 90)
    - White, E. E., Miss, to Williams, Gail (Box 91)
    - Williams, H. L., Mrs., to Wofford, Nancy L. (Box 92)
    - Wogen, Gladys, to Wyman, Ida (Box 93)
    - Wyndham, Olivia, to Zylstra, Frieda, and [No surname] Ada, to [No surname] Susanna (Box 94)
  - Biographical Volumes, (44 volumes)
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the surname or corporate name of the photographer or photographic studio and therein by the author or compiler of the material.
    This subseries consists primarily of biographical materials compiled by Palmquist and then bound by him into volumes. It also includes volumes, primarily of theses and dissertations, created by other authors.
    The content of the volumes mirrors the material in the biographical files and also includes a small group of correspondence with researchers and historians of photography.
    Dates attributed to compiled materials in this subseries reflect dates of compilation rather than the dates covered by the material in the particular volume.
    - Abbott, Berenice (1898-1991)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Berenice Abbott (1898-1991): Miscellaneous Notes, Volume 1, 1992 Dec (Box 95)
    - Allen, Frances Stebbins (1854-1941), and Mary Electa Allen (1858-1941)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Frances and Mary Allen of Deerfield, Massachusetts: Essays and Checklists, 1969-1993, circa 1993 (Box 96)
    - Armer, Laura Adams (1874-1963)
      - Conrotto, Eugene L., "Armer: Last Letters", 1978 Apr (Box 97)
        Master of Arts Thesis, California State University, Stanislaus
      - Myers, Roger, compiler, Laura Adams Armer Correspondence, 1924-1951, undated (Box 98)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Laura Adams Armer (1874-1963): Life Chronology and Notes, undated; (8 volumes) (Box 99-106)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Laura Adams Armer Photographs at the Wheelwright Museum of the American Indian (Santa Fe, New Mexico), 1993 (Box 107)
    - Bonney, Mabel Therese (circa 1896-1978)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Mabel Therese Bonney (circa 1896-1978): Miscellaneous Biographical Notes, circa 1992 (Box 108)
    - Brigman, Anne W. (1869-1950)
      - Brown, Leslie Kathleen. "'Staging the Mystical': The Photographs of Anne Brigman and the Mystical Philosophy of Edward Carpenter", 1998 (Box 109)
        Master of Arts Thesis, University of Texas at Austin
      - Hutchinson, Elizabeth W., "Naiads, Dryads and Nymphs: Anne Brigman and the Spiritual Landscape", 1987 (Box 110)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Anne W. Brigman (1869-1950): Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1993 (Box 111)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Correspondence: Anne W. Brigman and Alfred S. Stieglitz, 1903-1945, undated (Box 112)
      - Stern, Jenny, "Unleashing the Spirit: The Art of Isadora Duncan and Anne Brigman", 1991 Apr (Box 113)
        Master of Arts Thesis, San Francisco State University
      - Wallace, Robin Lynn, "The Glory of the Open: Spirituality and Nature in the Photography and Poetry of Anne Brigman", 2000 (Box 114)
        Master of Arts Thesis, University of Louisville
    - Bubey, Esther (born 1921)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Esther Bubley (1921- ): Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1990 (Box 115)
    - Cadby, Carine (born circa 1871)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Carine Cadby: Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1898-1933, circa 1997 (Box 116)
    - Carpenter, Helen McCowen (1836-1917)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Helen McCowen Carpenter (1838-1917): Collected Notes, circa 1989 (Box 117)
      - Peri, David W., compiler, "The Hudson Carpenter Estate and Its Collection" (Photographers Aurelius Ormando Carpenter, Helen McCowen Carpenter, Grace Carpenter Hudson and Dr. John Wilz Napier Hudson) Ukiah, California, 1977 Nov (Box 118)
    - Coleman, Emma Alfreda White
      - Fairbrother, Fay P., "Emma Alfreda White Coleman: Norman Pioneer, Photographer, and Businesswoman", 1993 (Box 119)
        Master of Arts Thesis, University of Oklahoma
    - Dahl-Wolfe, Louise
      - Edwards, Jennifer Somerville, "Louise Dahl-Wolfe: A Fashion Photographer Redefined", 1996 (Box 120)
        Master of Arts Thesis, University of Arizona
    - Eldridge, Sarah Louise Judd, (1802-1886)
      - Woolworth, Alan R., compiler, "Sarah Louise (Judd) Eldridge (1802-1886): First Known Photographer in Minnesota Territory", 1988-1995 (Box 121)
    - Fletcher, Christine B. (circa 1872-1962)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Christine B. Fletcher (circa 1872- ): Collected Notes as of January 2000, 2000 Jan (Box 122)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., and Rachel Ihara, "The Life and Still Life of Christine B. Fletcher (circa 1872-1961)", 2000 (Box 123)
    - Gilpin, Laura (1891-1970)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Laura Gilpin (1891-1970): Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1997 (Box 124)
    - Halsey, Louise Edwards (1872-1962)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, "Louise Edwards Halsey", circa 1978-1985 (Box 125)
    - Hilmer, Lucy (born 1945)
      - Hilmer, Lucy, "Birthday & Other Suits: A Journey from the Outside In," manuscript, 1994 (Box 126)
    - Johnston, Frances Benjamin (1864-1952)
      - Hannum, Gillian Greenhill, "Coming to Light: Frances Benjamin Johnston and the Foremost Women Photographers in America," manuscript, 1996 (Box 127)
    - Kasebier, Gertrude Stanton (1852-1934)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Gertrude Stanton Kasebier (1852-1934): Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1996 (Box 128)
    - Ladd, Ellen Elizabeth (1861-1922)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Nellie Ladd: Photographer of Old Denny, California, Miscellaneous Notes and Chronology, 1999 (Box 129)
    - Lange, Dorothea (1895-1965)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, Dorothea Lange (1895-1965): Miscellaneous Notes to 1999 (Box 130)
    - Noble, Callie (Fictitious character)
      - Werkley, Vicki Hessel, Taking the Redwoods: The Story of Callie Noble -- Photographer, manuscript, 1987 (Box 131)
    - Reece, Jane (1869-1961)
      - Chambers, Karen S., "Jane Reece: A Photographer's View of the Artist", 1977 (Box 132)
        Master of Arts Thesis, University of Cincinnati
    - Schoenfeld, Diana Lindsay (born 1949)
      - Schoenfeld, Diana Lindsay, "Symbol and Surrogate: An Interpretive Description of the Picture-Within-The-Picture in Photography," manuscript, 1984 (Box 133)
    - Ward, Catherine Weed Barnes (1851-1913)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, "Catherine Weed Barnes Ward: Collected Writings, 1889-1908," Volume 1, circa 1982-1992 (Box 134)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, "Catherine Weed Barnes: Life Chronology and Biographical Resources 1851-1913," Volume 2, circa 1982-1992 (Box 135)
    - Wiggins, Myra Albert (1869-1956)
      - Glauber, Carole, "The Witch of Kodakery: The Life and Times of Myra Albert Wiggins", 1993 (Box 136)
        Unpublished manuscript
    - Williams, Elizabeth "Tex" (born 1924)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., compiler, "Elizabeth 'Tex' Williams (1924- )", 1993 (Box 137)
    - Wolcott, Marion Post
      - MacKichan, Margaret Anna, "Marion Post Wolcott: Farm Security Administration Photographer in Eastern Kentucky", 1977 (Box 138)
        Master of Fine Arts Thesis, University of New Mexico
  - Volumes About Women Photographers in General, (75 volumes)
    This subseries is organized into three sections: volumes compiled by Peter Palmquist, general works about women photographers by other authors, and bibliographies about women in photographic literature compiled by Palmquist.
    This subseries consists of Palmquist's miscellaneous notes and photocopies of secondary material about women and photography, as well as inventories of his book collection about women and photography.
    - Volumes compiled by Palmquist
      - Women Photographers, Volumes 1-14
        - Volume 1: Statistics / Job Descriptions / Women's Photo Organizations / Bibliographic Notes, undated (Box 139)
        - Volume 2: Miscellaneous Articles, circa 1850-1995, undated (Box 140)
        - Volume 3: Exhibition Notes / Reviews and Art Photography, undated (Box 141)
        - Volume 4: Amateur Photography / Miscellaneous "Tid-Bits" about Women in Photography, Pre-History to the Present, undated (Box 142)
        - Volume 5: Various Notes on California Women Photographers Collected before 1987, undated (Box 143)
        - Volume 6: Regional and Miscellaneous Listing of Women Photographers / Various Compilers, undated (Box 144)
        - Volume 7: Miscellaneous Information through October 1997, 1997 Oct (Box 145)
        - Volumes 8-9: Miscellaneous Information through August 1998, 1997 Aug (Box 146-147)
        - Volume 10: Miscellaneous Information through December 1998, 1998 Dec (Box 148)
        - Volume 11: Miscellaneous Information through December 1999, 1999 Dec (Box 149)
        - Volume 12: Miscellaneous Information through September 2000, 2000 Sep (Box 150)
        - Volume 13: Miscellaneous Information through October 2001, 2001 Oct (Box 151)
        - Volume 14: Miscellaneous Information through December 2001, 2001 Dec (Box 152)
      - Writings By and About Women in the History of Photography, 1851-1990, undated; 20 volumes (Box 153-172)
        The volumes in the component do not run sequentially and their contents overlap in their date coverage
      - Women in California Photography before 1901, undated; 10 volumes (Box 173-182)